Guide to the Arnold Bennett Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Arnold Bennett collection
1899-1931
GEN MSS 323
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes and 1 portfolio)
Writings and correspondence by Arnold Bennett. Correspondence consists of letters by Bennett to others, including 70 to Frank Vernon, and 5 letters to Bennett from John Van Druten, accompanied by carbon typescript copies of Bennett's replies. The Writings include drafts of novels, essays, reviews, and playscripts by Bennett, production notes for the play "Cupid and Commonsense," and a memorandum of agreement concerning the production of the play "The Love Match."
Bennett, Arnold, 1867-1931
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded in series level notes. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile materials may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Arnold Bennett, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to September 1997 have been organized into five series: Series I, James M. Osborn Gift, Series II, Lansing V. Hammond Gift, Series III, Philip Neufeld Gift, Series IV, Charles A. Stonehill Gift, and Series V, Additional Materials, which consists of materials acquired from various other sources. Restricted Fragile Papers contains material from Series I.
Playscripts; Books and Persons; Don Juan de Marana a Play in Four Acts; Lord Raingo; Bennett, Arnold, 1867-1931; Van Druten, John, 1901-1957; Vernon, Frank, 1875-
- James M. Osborn Gift, 1909-1931; Series I; 0.8' (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of James M. Osborn, 1951
  - TNS and ALS to Virginia Fox-Brooks Vernon, London, 1928, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 4 ALS and 1 TLS from John Van Druten, [v.p.], 1929-30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Accompanied by carbon typescript copies of Arnold Bennett's replies, dated March 6, 1929; October 26, 1929; March 31, 1930; April 2, 1930
  - 70 ALS, TLS and APS to Frank Vernon, [v.p.], 1909-31 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    Accompanied by a letter from Bennett's secretary, Winifred Nerney, April 17, 1931. Letter dated Sep 14, 1919 is accompanied by pencil note in Frank Vernon's hand
  - The Crime: A Play in Four Acts, typescript of the scenario, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cupid and Common Sense, production notes of the play, autograph copy (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
    Contents: Stage directions, stage settings with sketches, list of properties. Accompanied by a typescript of the title page, synopses of scenes and remarks on the various characters in the play. Note on envelope: "apparently in the hand of Frank Vernon"
  - Don Juan, typescript copy of a sketch of a play in four acts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Accompanied by a rough sketch of the stage setting for one of the acts of Don Juan [?]
  - The Great Adventure: A Play of Fancy in Four Acts, typescript copy with autograph stage directions and corrections (Box 1, Folder 14-20)
    Published in N.Y. by George H. Doran [c1913]. Accompanied by a typed copy of the forward
  - The Love Match: "Memorandum of Agreement Between Arnold Bennett and Frank Vernon," concerning the production of the play: typescript copy, initialed and signed for Arnold Bennett, by A. N. Tayler, 1922 Jan 10 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Milestones: A Play in Three Acts, by Arnold Bennett and Edward Knoblauch, typescript copy with autograph stage directions and corrections (Box 2, Folder 22-31)
    Accompanied by another typescript copy of Milestones with a few autograph corrections. Accompanied by 2 typescript copies of "Forward to Milestones ," a stage plan of the Royalty Theatre, lists of the cast in Chicago and New York, a list of "Letters filed" and "List of cheques received" with a drawing of stage plan on verso. Milestones was published in London by Methuen & Co., ltd., 1912
  - Rivals for Rosamund, A Farce in One Act, 2 typescript copies (original and carbon), each with pencilled corrections and additions (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
    Includes carbon copy of a pen and ink sketch of the stage setting and an autograph manuscript of "Furniture property and plot"
- Lansing V. Hammond Gift, 1929; Series II; 0.1' (1/4 box)
  Gift of Lansing V. Hammond, 1962
  - "Debtors Who Have Short Memories," autograph manuscript essay, signed, London, 1929 Jan (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Concerning the state of veterans after World War I
  - "Don't Be Shocked," autograph manuscript essay, signed, London, 1929 Jan 31 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Concerning modern art
  - "Questions and Answers About Life," autograph manuscript essay, signed, London, 1929 Mar 9 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - "This Modern Living," autograph manuscript, signed, London, 1929 May 17 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Philip Neufeld Gift, 1916-1929; Series III; 0.2'(1/2 box)
  Gift of Philip Neufeld, 1958-1961
  - "Books and Persons," autograph manuscript, London, 1929 Mar 19 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    A critical review of Lytton Strachey's Elizabeth and Essex
  - "Edwin Alfred Rickards, A Personal Sketch," autograph manuscripts of a personal reminiscence, announcement of a book on Rickards, and a "postscript" (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Accompanied by typescripts. Published as the introduction to The Art of E. A. Rickards ..., London, 1920
  - Lord Raingo, TMS used in setting the American edition, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40-50)
    Acc #: 621220-b
  - "Mr. Arnold Bennett was coming out of the New Savoy Theatre...," autograph manuscript, London, 1929 Oct 16 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Imaginary interview written in third person. Accompanied by typescript
  - "No Smoke Without Fire," autograph manuscript, London, 1928 Oct 10-11 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Criticism of British law
  - "Souvenir Programme" of the 'Grand Special Concert' for the Wounded Allies Relief Committee, autograph manuscript, 1916 Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Accompanied by a form letter, in facsimile, advertising the concert
- Charles A. Stonehill Gift, 1927-1928; Series IV; 0.05' (1/8 box)
  Gift of Charles A. Stonehill, 1938
  - "Books & Persons," Reviews, in MS, of L. Riding's Contemporaries and snobs and of W. B. Yeats's The Tower, London, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    Mention is also made of A. N. Whitehead's Science and the Modern World
  - Two original manuscript reviews, signed, of Life and Letters of Joseph Conrad and Letters from Joseph Conrad, 1927, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Includes manuscript corrections and additions. Edited by G. Jean-Aubry
- Additional Materials, 1899-1930; Series V; 0.05' (1/8 box)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders
  - 2 ALS to William Morris Colles, Bedfordshire, 1901, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - ALS to Mrs. George Day, Hôtel Californie, Cannes, 1911 Dec 7 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - ALS to "My Dear Hueffer" [Ford Maddox Ford], Seine et Marne, France, 1909 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - 2 ALS to Cranstoun Metcalfe, London, 1899 Jun 2, 1900 Apr 12 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - ALS to F. Whelen, Avon, France, 1911 Aug 18 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - "Books & Persons," autograph manuscript, signed, London, 1930 Jul 12 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    Accompanied by a typed transcript. Discusses literary criticism in general and Sinclair Lewis and Harold Bell Wright in particular.
  - "Folk Song Quartet," autograph manuscript notes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 61a)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 1; portfolio
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 22 (Box PORT, folder 62)